<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="hack.typealiasing">
  <title>Type Aliasing</title>
  <para>
    Many programming languages allow existing types to be redefined as new type names. The C language has typedefs. OCaml has type abbreviations. PHP even has rudimentary mechanism with its <function>class_alias</function> function.
  </para>
  <para>
    Hack and HHVM are offering two ways to redefine type names: type aliasing and opaque type aliasing. Here is the syntax for each.
    <informalexample>
      <para><emphasis>Type Aliasing</emphasis></para>
      <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing1.php" />
      <para><emphasis>Opaque Type Aliasing</emphasis></para>
      <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing2.php" />
    </informalexample>
  </para>
  <para>
    Type aliases are declared outside of classes at the top-level. Also, the grammar on the RHS of the declaration is the same as would be put for type annotations on a parameter or return type. For example, take this function signature:
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing3.php" />
    </informalexample>
  </para>
  <para>
    A type alias that would replace <literal>(int, int)</literal> in <literal>foo()</literal> would look like:
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing4.php" />
    </informalexample>
  </para>
  <para>
    While type aliasing and opaque type aliases are very similar, there is a key difference around assignment compatibility to the original type. Unlike type aliases, Hack restricts opaque type aliases in a manner that only the file that defined the opaque type alias is allowed to access the underlying implementation.
  </para>

  <sect1 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.typealiasing">
    <title>Type Aliasing</title>
    <para>
      Type aliasing allows the redefining of an existing type name, but still refers to the existing type's underlying implementation. For example:
      <informalexample>
        <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing5.php" />
        <para><emphasis>File2.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing6.php" />
        &example.outputs;
        <screen>
<![CDATA[
9
]]>
        </screen>
        <para>
          <literal>NotSoSecret</literal> is a pure alias for an <literal>int</literal> and has the all the underlying capability of an <literal>int</literal>.
        </para>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.opaquetypealiasing">
    <title>Opaque Type Aliasing</title>
    <para>
      Opaque type aliasing bear some similarity to normal type aliases. There is a key difference, however. Unlike type aliases, Hack restricts opaque type aliases in such a manner that only the file that defined the opaque type is allowed to access the underlying implementation. For example:
      <informalexample>
        <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing7.php" />
        <para><emphasis>File2.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing8.php" />
        <para>
          The file where <literal>SecretID</literal> is defined allows <literal>int</literal> operations such as add and subtract to be performed. However, in any other file Hack will throw an error when trying to use <literal>int</literal> operations on something declared as a <literal>SecretID</literal>
        </para>
        &example.outputs;
        <screen>
<![CDATA[
File "File2.php", line 7, characters 14-17:
Typing error
File "File2.php", line 7, characters 14-17:
This is an int/float because this is used in an arithmetic operation
File "File2.php", line 6, characters 31-38:
It is incompatible with an object of type SecretID
]]>
        </screen>
        <para>
          Note, however, the above code in <literal>File2.php</literal> will run fine in HHVM since at runtime <literal>SecretID</literal> is indeed just an <literal>int</literal>.
        </para>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
    <para>
      Here is another example where an opaque type alias is created from a <literal>string</literal>. The concatenation operator (<literal>.</literal>) can be used in the file where the opaque type alias is defined, but not in other files.
      <informalexample>
        <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing9.php" />
        <para><emphasis>File2.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing10.php" />
        &example.outputs;
        <screen>
<![CDATA[
File "File2.php", line 8, characters 10-17:
Invalid return type
File "File2.php", line 7, characters 39-50:
This is an object of type SecretString
File "File2.php", line 8, characters 10-17:
It is incompatible with a string because this is the result of a concatenation
]]>
        </screen>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.opaquewithconstraints">
    <title>Opaque Type Aliases with Constraints</title>
    <para>
      Normally, an opaque type alias does not allow the underlying representation of its type to be accessed (modulo the file in which the opaque type alias is defined). This is still true in principle. However, Hack has added the ability to add type constraints to opaque type aliases. Opaque type aliases with constraints still don't allow access to the underlying representation of the type alias, but they do allow access to the representation represented by the constraint. This is best illustrated with an example.
      <informalexample>
        <para><emphasis>ot1.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing11.php" />
        <para><emphasis>ot2.php</emphasis></para>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing12.php" />
        &example.outputs;
        <screen>
<![CDATA[
/tmp/ot2/ot2.php:7:22,34: Invalid argument (Typing[4110])
  /tmp/ot2/ot1.php:20:22,24: This is an int
  /tmp/ot2/ot1.php:13:30,35: It is incompatible with an object of type OddInt
/tmp/ot2/ot2.php:7:7,19: Invalid argument (Typing[4110])
  /tmp/ot2/ot1.php:20:14,16: This is an int
  /tmp/ot2/ot1.php:13:30,35: It is incompatible with an object of type OddInt
]]>
        </screen>
        <para>
          The code above should look relatively familiar in the context of
          opaque type aliasing. Using <literal>newtype</literal>, opaque type
          aliases are declared called <literal> EvenInt</literal> and
          <literal>OddInt</literal>. However, this time the alias
          <literal>EvenInt</literal> has a <literal>int</literal> constraint on
          it. This means that <literal>EvenInt</literal>s can be used as
          <literal>int</literal>s in, for example, function calls (e.g.
          <literal>add(int, int)</literal>) that take an
          <literal>int</literal>. However, since <literal>OddInt</literal> does
          not have the <literal>int</literal> constraint,
          <literal>OddInt</literal>s cannot be passed into functions that take
          an <literal>int</literal>.
        </para>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>
        The following syntax is not yet supported by the Hack type checker...
        <informalexample>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing13.php" />
      </informalexample>
      </para>
    </warning>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples">
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here are some further examples on using type aliases and opaque type aliases.
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples.opaqueconstruction">
      <title>Opaque Type Aliases and Construction</title>
      <para>
        Here is an example of using a opaque type aliases that defines the representation of a point on the (x,y) plane.
        <informalexample>
          <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing14.php" />
          <para>
            Here is the test code:
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Test.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing15.php" />
          <para>
            Since a opaque type alias was used, the underlying implementation of <literal>Point</literal> (i.e., <literal>tuple</literal>) cannot be accessed outside of the file it was defined. Thus, it is important that mechanisms are added to be able to construct a representation of the opaque type. In this case, <literal>createPoint()</literal> was defined to be able to do this construction. This is the HHVM output from running the above test code:
          </para>
          &example.outputs;
          <screen>
<![CDATA[
2.8284271247462
]]>
          </screen>
        </informalexample>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples.stringencoding">
      <title>String Encoding</title>
      <para>
        Here is an example where string encodings are being type aliased.
      </para>
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing16.php" />
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing17.php" />
        <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing18.php" />
        &example.outputs;
        <screen>
<![CDATA[
type_aliasing_2.php:11:10,11: Invalid return type
  type_aliasing_2.php:8:18,28: This is an object of type UTF8_string
  type_aliasing_2.php:10:8,35: It is incompatible with a string because this is the result of a concatenation
]]>
        </screen>
        <para>
          Since we are using opaque type aliases, we cannot concatenate a UTF8_string and UTF16_string together, since we do not have access to the underlying string type, from the Hack type checker point of view. Of course, this will run in HHVM just fine.
        </para>
      </informalexample>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples.reducingconversionerrors">
      <title>Reducing Conversion Errors</title>
      <para>
        This example demonstrates how opaque type aliases can help reduce conversion errors. Taking a class that deals with seconds, minutes and hours, the "old" way of creating such a class may have been:
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing19.php" />
          <para>
            While a careful reading and understanding of the code is pretty clear what values should be passed to each method, and the developer may be able to create some internal checks to rule out bad values, anything can be passed to these functions. They are just <literal>int</literal>s after all. Minutes may be passed to <literal>funcForSeconds()</literal>, for example. Now look at the same class implemented using opaque type aliases:
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing20.php" />
          <para>
            Any file outside of the one where the opaque type alias is declared and defined will not be able use the underlying representation to pass in errant values to the methods. Thus, to the outside world, <literal>Seconds</literal> are actually seconds and not <literal>int</literal>s. Here is test code for the above that should produce a type error:
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Test.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing21.php" />
          &example.outputs;
          <screen>
<![CDATA[
ot_conversion_errors_2.php:7:13,19: Wrong type hint
ot_conversion_errors_2.php:7:13,19: This is an object of type Seconds
ot_conversion_errors_2.php:7:26,26: It is incompatible with an int
]]>
          </screen>
          <para>
            Again, the above code will run correctly in HHVM. It just won't type check correctly through the Hack type checker.
          </para>
        </informalexample>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples.generics">
      <title>Generics</title>
      <para>
        Type aliases and opaque type aliases can be used successfully with generic types. Suppose a <literal>Vector&lt;Vector&lt;T&gt;&gt;</literal>. That looks like a matrix. And it makes perfect sense to redefine the name of <literal>Vector&lt;Vector&lt;T&gt;&gt;</literal> as a <literal>Matrix&lt;T&gt;</literal>.
        <informalexample>
          <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing22.php" />
          <para><emphasis>File2.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing23.php" />
        </informalexample>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples.phantomtypes">
      <title>Phantom Types</title>
      <para>
        Take this piece of code that includes a type alias:
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing24.php" />
          &example.outputs;
          <screen>
<![CDATA[
object(FooPhantom)#1 (0) {
}
string(22) "O:10:"FooPhantom":0:{}"
object(FooPhantom)#2 (0) {
}
]]>
          </screen>
          <para>
            This example shows what is called a &quot;phantom&quot; type. The reason for this is that the right hand side of the typedef does not explicitly mention the type parameter <literal>T</literal> used on the left hand side of the typedef. In reality, <literal>Serialized&lt;T&gt;</literal> is just a string. However, the type checker carries around the information about what type a use of the typedef had originally. For example, calling <literal>serialize_phantom()</literal> with a <literal>FooPhantom</literal> allows the type checker to remember that a <literal>FooPhantom</literal> was the original type. Thus a call to <literal>unserialize_phantom()</literal> will return a <literal>FooPhantom()</literal>.
          </para>
        </informalexample>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.examples.enums">
      <title>Enums</title>
      <para>
        Opaque type aliases can be used to mimic C++ style enumerations.
        <informalexample>
          <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing25.php" />
          <para><emphasis>File1.php</emphasis></para>
          <programlisting role="php" location="hack.typealiasing26.php" />
        </informalexample>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="hack.typealiasing.summary">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para>
      Type aliasing and opaque type aliasing provide PHP developers a clean way to redefine type names (a la C typedefs). Type aliases are just that, aliases. There are no restrictions to the access of the existing type on which the alias was created. Opaque type aliases have more restrictions. As far as the Hack type checker is concerned, access to the existing type can only occur in the file where the opaque type alias is defined. However, at runtime, HHVM will still consider an opaque type alias to be the underlying type at run time as far as operations, etc. are concerned.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:t
indent-tabs-mode:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-default-dtd-file:"~/.phpdoc/manual.ced"
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
vim600: syn=xml fen fdm=syntax fdl=2 si
vim: et tw=78 syn=sgml
vi: ts=1 sw=1
-->
